UMANG MEHTA

Location: Austin, TX umangrmehta.github.io

Email: <u>umangrmehta@gmail.com</u> <u>linkedin.com/in/umangrmehta</u>

Cell: +1 (812) 955-9507 github.com/umangrmehta

OBJECTIVE

I aspire to work in the field of Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, and Cognitive Science & Engineering with applications involving Speech Recognition, Natural Language Processing, and Conversational AI.

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Machine Learning Engineer & Data Scientist with 4.5 years of active research & development experience in Machine Learning (ML), Neural Networks, Natural Language Processing (NLP), MLOps, Big Data Engineering, Social Media Mining, Conversational AI, Information Extraction (IE), Knowledge Graph, Predictive Analytics with Python & Scala and 5 years of professional experience as Full-Stack Software Engineer & Team Mentor with expertise in Database & Java.

EDUCATION

Master's Degree in Data Science

MAY 2019

Luddy School of Informatics Computing and Engineering (SICE), Indiana University, Bloomington Major Courses: Advanced NLP, Machine Learning, Deep Learning Systems, Data Mining, Elements of AI, Algorithms Design and Analysis, Statistical Inference, Advanced Database Concepts, High-Performance Big Data Systems. GPA: 3.6

Bachelor's Degree in Computer Engineering

MAY 2013

K J Somaiya College of Engineering (KJSCE), Mumbai University, India Graduated with SECOND Class, aggregate 59.77% equivalent to GPA 3.21.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Java (7 yrs), Scala (3 yrs), Python (4.5 yrs), Javascript (5 yrs), C/C++, GraphQL,

Gremlin, R, MATLAB, Groovy, PHP

Database: RDBMS- MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle; NoSQL- MongoDB, Apache Solr, Elasticsearch,

Redis, DynamoDB; Graph - Neo4J, JanusGraph, Dgraph

Web Design: HTML5-CSS3, React, AngularJS, JQuery, UnderscoreJS, Bootstrap, Polymer

Frameworks: NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, Plotly, Tableau, Spring Framework, Hibernate ORM, Flask,

FastAPI, Play Framework, Morphia, Smack(XMPP), JSSC, Apache HTTP, PHP-MySQL,

Symfony Framework, Doctrine ORM, NetworkX, Django, ND4J

Machine Learning: TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, Deeplearning4J, Scikit-Learn

NLP Toolkits: Rasa, NLTK, Stanford CoreNLP, Spacy, OpenNLP, Spark NLP, Polyglot, Gensim

Big Data: Hadoop, Spark, Kafka, Snowflake, Apache Hive, AWS Redshift

Project Utility: VCS - Git, SVN; Dependency - Maven, Gradle, Composer, NPM; SCRUM - Jira

Servers: Apache 2, Apache Tomcat 7-8, NodeJS, Netty, Openfire, Nginx, WildFly

Deployment Tools: Docker, Kubernetes, AWS EC2, AWS Lambda, AWS S3, AWS EMR, AWS Batch, AWS

Cloud Development Kit (CDK), Jenkins, BitBucket, GitHub

Data & ML Ops: AWS Sagemaker, AWS Step Function, Databricks, MLFlow, Apache Airflow

OS: Ubuntu(Linux), Windows, macOS

Cloud: Amazon Web Services(AWS), Google Cloud Services(GCS)

Certification: Oracle Certified Professional JavaSE6 Programmer,

DeepLearning.AI TensorFlow Developer

WORK EXPERIENCE

Audible - An Amazon Company, Austin, TX

SDE -Machine Learning Engineering (Full-Time)

NOV 2021 - APRIL 2023

- Developed workflows using AWS components like Sagemaker, Lambda, Batch, Glue, EMR & Step Functions as building blocks for creating pipelines with stages for training, validation, scoring, publishing, load testing & deployment to production for Machine Learning Models
- Worked on the Frontend with **React** and Backend with **FastAPI & AWS DynamoDB** for the platform used for hosting Machine Learning pipelines using the stages mentioned earlier
- Used AWS Cloud Development Kit (CDK) to deploy and manage Cloud Resources on AWS
- Worked with Data Scientists to make the model code production ready and deploy them as containers to the AWS ECS repository for AWS Sagemaker to run Training and Inferencing
- Overall my work on Machine Learning Platform resulted in reducing engineering efforts of Data Science by 75%
- Collaborated with Data Scientists to develop and deploy multiple Machine Learning Models including
 Predictive Analytics, Text Classification, Anomaly Detection and Reinforcement Learning
- Maintained code and development pipeline using **Git**.
- Followed SCRUM Agile Development processes using Jira.
- Technologies & Tools: Python, Scala, Java, Apache Spark, Git, AWS Sagemaker, AWS Step Functions, AWS Batch, AWS Glue, AWS DynamoDB, AWS CDK, AWS ECS, AWS EMR, AWS Lambda, AWS S3, AWS CloudFormation, Linux

Capital One, Chicago, IL Data Engineer

JAN 2019 - OCT 2021

- Developed Data Processing Pipeline using **Apache Spark** and **Scala** to process Credit Card Requests in batches with joining data from other sources and APIs and make the final output available for Card Embossing Process which will replace the existing mainframe system making the process more efficient by 70%.
- Integrated Streaming Data Pipeline using **Apache Kafka** in various data pipelines.
- Built data pipelines for data transfer and warehousing using Enterprise File Gateway, Snowflake,
 Databricks and Apache Spark for incoming data from external sources to be used by analytics intents like Anti-Money Laundering and Fraud Detection using Anomaly Detection.
- Built serverless functions using **Python** to spin up a transient **AWS EMR** to run the data pipelines.
- Used AWS Lambda, AWS EMR, AWS CloudFormation and AWS S3 for production deployment.
- Maintained code and development pipeline using **Git** on **GitHub**.
- Followed SCRUM Agile Development processes using Jira.
- **Technologies & Tools:** Scala, Java, Apache Spark, Apache Kafka, Git, AWS EC2, AWS EMR, AWS Lambda, AWS S3, AWS CloudFormation, Databricks, Linux, Spring

Hello Nesh Inc., Houston, TX Data Scientist - NLP & AI

JUNE 2019 - OCT 2019

- Implemented **Conversational AI** Assistant backend using **Rasa** framework in **Python** with a pipeline consisting of **Intent Classifier**, **Spacy**, **CRF Entity Extractor**, **POS Tagging** and **Constituent Parsing**.
- Trained and deployed **Deep Learning Neural Network** models with **Dense Neural Networks** and **LSTM** for Text Classification using **TensorFlow**, **Keras** and **SciKit-Learn** through **AWS Sagemaker** in **Python**.
- Built a Question Answer System based on **BERT** in **Python** served using **Flask** on **AWS EC2**.
- Developed a Knowledge Extraction pipeline for 100k+ public documents with stages and components involving Web Scraping and HTML Parsing with BeautifulSoup; Semantic Extraction using Named Entity Recognition(NER), Constituent Parsing & Anaphora Resolution with Spacy, Duckling and Conditional Random Fields; Topic Modeling with TextRazor and Gensim in Python deployed through AWS EC2, AWS DynamoDB and AWS S3.
- Developed a Knowledge Graph using Dgraph as graph database and GraphQL as query language to represent the extracted knowledge with 1M+ entities, deployed on Linux using Docker and AWS EC2.

- Programmed a Data Access Layer for Knowledge Graph in NodeJS and Javascript deployed through AWS Lambda.
- Conceptualized and developed PoC of Diagnostic Analysis and Predictive Analytics of Oil Well Failure
 with Maximum-Likelihood(MLE) and Maximum-A-Priori(MAP) estimations and
 Expectation-Maximization(EM) Algorithm with basic feature engineering using NumPy, SciPy,
 Pandas and SciKit-Learn in Python.
- Maintained code and development pipeline using **Git** on **Bitbucket**.
- Followed SCRUM Agile Development processes using Jira.
- Technologies & Tools: Python, Java, Rasa, TensorFlow, Keras, SciKit-Learn, BERT, Stanford CoreNLP, Spacy, TextRazor, Gensim, Dash by Plotly, NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, Flask, Dgraph, Docker, Kubernetes, Nginx, Git, AWS EC2, AWS S3, AWS RDS, AWS Lambda, AWS Sagemaker, AWS DynamoDB, Gremlin, JanusGraph, Linux, Javascript, NodeJS

$\textbf{Kelley School of Business,} \ \textbf{Bloomington, IN}$

JUNE 2018 - MAY 2019

Graduate Research Assistant under Prof. Matthew Josefy

- Worked under Prof. Matthew Josefy utilizing ML & NLP for research on Strategy & Entrepreneurship.
- Researched and implemented NLP methods to extract relevant information from **50k+** SEC Filings.
- Developed **predictive models** to analyze the business model and board leadership structure of companies and used them for **diagnostic analysis** as well.
- Built Text Classifiers using NLTK & SciKit-Learn with 90% accuracy measured with 10-Fold Cross-Validation.
- Built ML models using **NumPy**, **Pandas** and **SciKit-Learn** in **Python**.
- Implemented Semantic Extraction with NER using Stanford CoreNLP and Spacy in Java and Python.
- Integrated a download and parsing pipeline for SEC Filings using **BeautifulSoup** in **Python**.
- Maintained code and development pipeline using Git on GitHub.
- Deployed the projects on an on-premise **Windows** system.
- **Technologies & Tools:** Python, Java, NumPy, SciKit-Learn, Pandas, Stanford CoreNLP, Spacy, Git, TensorFlow, Keras, BeautifulSoup, Windows

AriaData Inc.(Aridat), Bloomington, IN *NLP Research Engineer (Unpaid Position)*

FEB 2018 - MAY 2019

- Built an analytics engine to determine the critical reception of an artist's work based on chatter on social media
- Lead and advised on the research and implementations of advanced NLP methods to improve the efficiency of Sentiment Classifier and add new functionality to improvise analytics provided to artists.
- Developed a Data Preprocessing and Feature Engineering module using NLTK with steps involving POS Tagging, Stop Words Removal, Stemming and Lemmatization, Negation Handling, N-gram and Sentiment Scores using Afinn and TextBlob.
- Built Sentiment Classifier using an **ensemble** of **Naïve Bayes** and **Multiclass Logistic Regression** to classify tweets from artists as +1, 0 and -1 and implemented metrics to analyze sentiment distribution over different demographics.
- Deployed the project on an on-premise **Linux** system.
- **Technologies & Tools:** Python, Java, Numpy, Scikit-Learn, Pandas, Stanford CoreNLP, NLTK, Afinn, TextBlob, MongoDB, Git, Matplotlib, Plotly, TensorFlow, Keras, Linux

Vitruvian Technologies Pvt. Ltd.(VTPL), Mumbai, India Senior Developer & Team Mentor

JUNE 2014 - JULY 2017

- Developed functionalities for web-based ERP and CRM systems in the domain of Real Estate.
- Collaborated in a team of 12 for project development including Object Oriented Programming using Spring in Java & Groovy and Reactive Programming using Play in Scala
- Handled Data Structure & Database Design in Java, Hibernate & MySQL
- Designed and developed Web Applications with HTML 5, CSS 3, Javascript, Jquery, AngularJS, UnderscoreJS, Spring MVC in Java & Laravel in PHP
- Built Full-Text Search functionalities with Apache Solr and ElasticSearch

- Developed a routing software to redirect users to different tenant clusters based on the user logging in through a central login page using **Java**.
- Deployed projects using AWS EC2, AWS S3, AWS RDS, AWS Route53, AWS Cloud CDN and Linux
- Used Git and SVN as version control systems for different projects
- Lead, trained and mentored a sub-team of 5 throughout the development of the projects
- Contributed to the Core Framework, proprietarily used by the firm for project development.
- Technologies & Tools: Java, Scala, Groovy, Spring Framework, Hibernate ORM, MySQL, Apache Solr, ElasticSearch, HTML 5, CSS 3, Javascript, AngularJS, UnderscoreJS, Bootstrap, AJAX, Jquery, PHP, Laravel Framework, Play Framework, Git, SVN, AWS EC2, AWS S3, AWS RDS, AWS Route53, AWS Cloud CDN, Linux

Algonation, Mumbai, India

JUNE 2013 - MAY 2014

- Co-founder, Developer
 - Developed websites, web portals and mobile apps using HTML 5, CSS 3, Bootstrap, Javascript, AJAX,
 Jquery, PHP and MySQL for small and medium scale enterprises.
 - Built IM Chat Apps using Java, XMPP, Smack and Openfire on Android OS.
 - Built server software for TCP Layer Protocols customized for cloud-based industrial requirements with **Java**, **Netty**, **RabbitMQ** and **MySQL** deployed on **Linux** using **Google Cloud Services**.
 - Developed standalone and distributed software for some stages of manufacturing production lines using Java and JavaFX for Windows.
 - Mentored and trained groups of 3-4 undergraduate interns for developing industry level projects.
 - **Technologies & Tools:** Java, PHP, HTML 5, CSS 3, Bootstrap, Javascript, AJAX, Jquery, PHP, RabbitMQ, Netty, JavaFX, Openfire, Smack, XMPP, MySQL, Linux, Windows, Google Cloud Services

Research Innovation Incubation Design Laboratory (Riidl), Mumbai, India Software Engineer Intern

JUNE 2012 - MAY 2013

- Developed a web-based ERP application for educational institutes using **HTML**, **CSS**, **Bootstrap**, **Javascript**, **PHP**.
- Designed the data structures & schema and managed the database transactions using MySQL
- Built mobile App for the ERP using **Android SDK** for **Android** phones and **Java ME** for feature phones
- Deployed the ERP on a hosting service using cPanel.
- Technologies & Tools: Java, PHP, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Javascript, MySQL, Java ME, Android SDK

INDEPENDENT PROJECTS

Sentiment Classification — Using ELMo, BERT, LSTM, CNN in TensorFlow

• https://github.com/umangrmehta/tf-text-classifier

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Neural Conversation Model — Seq2Seq Learning using LSTM/RNN

AUG 2018 - DEC 2018

- Built a Proof of Concept(PoC) for Sequence-to-Sequence (Seq2Seq) Learning for a Neural Conversation Model with Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) and Recurrent Neural Networks (RNN) using Deeplearning4J (DL4J) library.
- Trained Model on Cornell Movie-Dialog Corpus.
- Experimented with High-Performance Computing (HPC) optimization options in DL4J.
- Experimented with Big Data System coupling with DL4J for Hadoop and Spark.
- Technologies & Tools: Java, DL4J, ND4J, Hadoop, Spark, Intel DAAL, Git, Linux

OpenIE — Open-Domain Information Extraction

MAY 2018 - PRESENT

- Worked for a research project under computational linguistics faculty at IU Prof. Damir Cavar for processing unstructured text to extract data, knowledge, entities and relations.
- Enabling semantic search with concept abstraction and linking concepts to concepts in large knowledge graphs like YAGO, DBPedia and Microsoft Concept Graph.
- **Technologies & Tools**: Python, Java, Numpy, Scikit-Learn, Pandas, Stanford CoreNLP, Spacy, OpenNLP, NLTK, Neo4J, Django, Git, WildFly, Linux

Speech Prosody and Pragmatics — Detecting Prosody and Pragmatics of spoken language MAY 2018 - PRESENT

- Working under computational linguistics faculty at IU Prof. Damir Cavar for this research project focusing on prosody, intonation contour detection, focus and stress pattern analysis for the processing of semantic and pragmatic aspects of spoken language.
- Technologies & Tools: Python, Java, Numpy, Scikit-Learn, Pandas, Google Cloud Speech API, Git

Image Orientation — Classifier using Neural Network and Adaboost

DEC 2017

- Developed a Multi-Layer Feed-Forward Neural Network and an AdaBoost classifier in collaboration with 2 people to identify the orientation of an image.
- Achieved accuracy of over 71% in Neural Network and over 67% in Adaboost on a test set of 1000 images trained on a corpus of over 36000 images.
- Technologies & Tools: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Git, Linux

Part of Speech — Tagging using Hidden Markov Model

NOV 2017

- Developed a program in collaboration with 2 people to identify parts of speech for English words in a sentence using Hidden Markov Model and Viterbi Algorithm.
- Achieved a word accuracy of over 95% and sentence accuracy of over 54% on a test set of 2000 sentences consisting of over 29000 words trained on a corpus of over 44000 sentences.
- Technologies & Tools: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Git, Linux

Pichu — Simplified Version of Chess

OCT 2017

- Collaborated in a group of 3 people to develop a program in Python using the Minimax Algorithm to recommend a chess move for a given board state.
- Used Object Oriented Programming in Python to maintain the game states.
- **Technologies & Tools:** Python, Git, Linux

LEADERSHIP

Data Science Club at Indiana University

FEB 2018 - FEB 2019

President and Treasurer

- Perfected the foundational structure of the Club Leadership.
- Organized hackathon for analyzing the opioid crisis in collaboration with SPEA at Indiana University.
- Spearheaded the initiative of monthly Newsletter and a semester wise e-Magazine.

Students' Council, K J Somaiya College of Engineering, Mumbai *Creative Head*

JUNE 2011 - MAY 2012

- Organized Technical and Cultural Festivals in KJSCE as Creative Head of the Organizing Committee.
- Headed the Creative Team for Kshitij, the Annual College Magazine of KJSCE.

EXTRA-CURRICULAR

- Author and Editor of a Entertainment review blog "The Minimalist Critic" on Medium.
- Won 2 consecutive Annual Chili Cook-offs in 2017 and 2018 organized by SICE at Indiana University.
- Organized Bollywood Quiz as Event Head in Symphony, the Annual Cultural Festival of KJSCE in 2011.
- Volunteered in the Infra and Logistics Team for Technical and Cultural Festivals in KJSCE from 2009 to 2011.
- As a hobby writer, got my poetic verses published in Kshitij, the Annual College Magazine of KJSCE and articles on topics of technology published in the Technical Magazine of the Computer Society of India, KJSCE Chapter.